You got your notebook,
let's go.
Welcome to CN Live episode 7. I'm Joe
Lauria, editor-in-chief of Consortium
News.
And I'm Elizabeth Goss.
On today's program, we'll be discussing
the coming 9/11 trial announced today
with John Kiriakou.
More than 19 years after the September
11th, 2001, five men will stand in a
military court in Guantanamo Bay, Cuba
for the terrorist attacks, a US military
judge said today. The trial will begin
on January 11th, 2021 and will be before
a military jury. The government has
until October 1st to turn over discovery
materials to the defense. Defense
attorneys want confessions thrown out
for their clients that they say were
elicited under torture.
Joining us to discuss this is someone
who was personally involved in events
related to this coming trial, former CIA
agent John Kiriakou. John led the
capture of Abu Zubaydah, Osama bin
Laden's chief lieutenant, and he blew
the whistle on the CIA torture program,
which figures significantly in this
case.
Hey John, welcome to CN Live.
Thank you. Thanks so much for having me,
Joe. I've been looking forward to this.
Well, thank you, John. I've got really
four burning questions and I'm not sure
which order to begin asking you, but
I'll start right away.
Is there any way these guys could get a
fair trial in a military court if it's a
US military jury? How could that hardly
be considered a jury of
of their peers?
Yeah, this is it's just not possible
to get a fair trial. It's literally not
possible. And let me tell you something,
too. When
when we first started capturing al-Qaeda
prisoners in Pakistan in January of
2002, I was the chief of CIA
counterterrorism operations there. And
we hadn't caught any prisoners in
Pakistan. They were all in Afghanistan.
And those prisoners had been held in
Afghanistan. Well, we started capturing
them in Pakistan and I simply didn't
know what to do with them. So, I called
CIA headquarters and I said, "What do
you want me to do with these guys?
They're starting to accumulate."
And I was told
to put them on a military transport
plane and send them to Guantanamo Bay,
Cuba.
And I said, "Cuba?
Why would I send them to Cuba?"
And I was told that they had come up
with a plan at headquarters that we put
them all in Cuba, they'll sit there for
two or three weeks until the appropriate
federal district court can be identified
where they would be tried, and then they
would be sent from Guantanamo to either
Washington, New York, or Boston to face
trial in federal civilian court. And I
thought, "Well, that's a great idea. If
we have evidence that they've committed
these terrible crimes of September 11th,
they need to get in front of a jury as
quickly as possible and be punished for
their crimes." And we began sending
everybody to Guantanamo. Everybody
except, that is, the highest profile
prisoners. In the beginning, it was Abu
Zubaydah, who I captured on March 22nd,
2002. But then we began adding
high-profile prisoners. Ramzi bin
al-Shibh, who allegedly masterminded the
USS Cole bombing, uh the various um
attackers of the American Embassies in
Africa. Finally, Khalid Sheikh Mohammed
in uh August of 2002. He was allegedly
the mastermind of the 9/11 attacks. But
instead of sending them to Guantanamo
and then on to federal district court,
they were sent to secret prisons.
I can't say where, even though it's been
reported widely in the press. Uh the CIA
has never declassified the information.
But at those prisons, crimes against
humanity took place. Their human rights,
their civil rights, their civil
were all violated. And not surprisingly,
they confessed to everything from the
9/11 attacks
to kidnapping the Lindbergh baby.
And so, what do you do with that
information? You can't do anything
because we have a constitution in this
country. You know, Joe, it's no accident
that these trials didn't take place in
2003 or four or five or any year between
then and today.
Twice before, military judges said that
they were going to hold trials,
especially of Khalid Sheikh Mohammed,
Ramzi Binalshibh, and Khalid Sheikh
Mohammed's nephew, Ammar al-Baluchi.
Those trials never took place, and the
reason they never took place is because
even the military judges recognized that
because the CIA had tortured every one
of these men, literally nothing that
they said to implicate themselves could
be used against them.
So, how in the world there's going to be
a fair trial in January of 2021
when it was impossible every year before
that is a mystery to me.
Well, next month, according to The New
York Times, there'll be a hearing in
this case on whether or not those
confessions should be thrown out, a
motion by the defense, because in fact,
as you said, the confessions were
yielded under torture. What you've just
said is the military judges all realized
that, but
uh well, I wouldn't be surprised, would
you, if the defense loses
that motion and and the confessions are
not thrown out?
I wouldn't be surprised if the defense
loses and the and
and they're not thrown out. But, there's
another issue here, too.
Um and that is
how are the defendants and their
attorneys going to be able to
interview or cross-examine or
interrogate those human sources who
identified the locations of these men
that allowed the CIA to capture them?
Or, if it wasn't human intelligence that
led to their locations, if it was
signals intelligence or some other kind
of clandestine method, those sources and
methods are going to have to be revealed
to the defense team so that the
defendants can defend themselves, and
the CIA would never ever allow such a
thing to happen.
So, that's not going to happen, man.
Now, now when you said the judges
already knew that there was torture
involved, was that before you public
when public with the torture program or
after?
No.
Um no, it was it was after. The judges
knew that there was torture involved in
the military interrogation program
before I went public uh because of Abu
Ghraib and because of a courageous uh
Navy civilian whistleblower in 2005.
But, what the CIA was doing was still a
mystery. There was one Army um enlisted
man at Guantanamo, Joe Hickman. Uh
Joe just happened to be
the guard on duty uh when Abu Zubaydah
arrived on a secret flight to
Guantanamo, and custody was turned over
from the CIA to the Department of the
Army. Uh Joe
spoke with Abu Zubaydah. Abu Zubaydah
told Joe that he had been tortured, and
then Joe kept his eyes open and noticed
a couple of times when Americans wearing
civilian clothes not answering to the
military would take prisoners out of
their cells and into a room that Joe was
told was off-limits to the military.
And then those prisoners turned up dead
the next morning, and their deaths were
ruled suicides.
Uh Joe blew the whistle.
Not many people listened to him,
but uh but he went public, and that was
before I ever did.
You led the arrest recently of Zubaydah.
Why is he the chief lieutenant of Osama
bin Laden himself?
Well, that's that's the $64,000
isn't he being put on trial here?
Yeah. That's the $64,000 question right
there.
Uh Joe Joe Hickman and I actually wrote
a book about about this called The
Convenient Terrorist.
In February of 2002, February 6th, 2002,
I was called into the uh US Embassy very
early in the morning. Um I was met there
by every senior intelligence officer in
country as well as the FBI's legal
attaché. And I was told that Abu
Zubaydah was somewhere in Pakistan and
that we had to catch him. And I'm
embarrassed to tell you that I had to
sit there with a very serious look on my
face thinking to myself,
Abu Zubaydah, that name kind of rings a
bell to me, but I don't have any idea
really who this guy is.
And then I was told, Abu Zubaydah, he's
the number three in Al-Qaeda. And I
vaguely remembered reading something in
Time magazine saying that he was the
number three in Al-Qaeda. Okay,
I'm happy to get with the program. Let's
go look for the guy. We'll try and catch
him. In fact, he was not the number
three in in Al-Qaeda. He was never a
member of Al-Qaeda. He never pledged
fealty to Al-Qaeda or to Osama bin
Laden. He was a bad guy. He had
established both of Al-Qaeda's training
camps in southern Afghanistan as
something like a contractor. He created
and maintained Al-Qaeda's safe house in
Peshawar, Pakistan called the House of
Martyrs.
But he never actually joined Al-Qaeda
and he certainly was not the number
three.
Besides that, and this is the real rub,
and this is why Abu Zubaydah is not
going on trial with the rest of these
guys.
There were two Abu Zubaydahs. There were
two men, first cousins, who had the same
name. Now, when you have one Abu
Zubaydah file and the other Abu Zubaydah
file, and you don't know that they're
two different people, and you put them
together, you have a file that looks
like a terrorist Superman.
He's in America. He's in Jordan. He's in
Saudi Arabia. He's in Afghanistan. My
god, this guy is everywhere all at the
same time. And he's opening up safe
houses and he's opening up training
camps and he's the number three in
Al-Qaeda and he's robbing a bank in
Bozeman, Montana.
Well, it it's frightening.
But it was two guys. It wasn't the same
guy. And so all these things that we
accused Abu Zubaydah of doing,
all these things that we tried to get
him to admit to under torture,
were false.
They were done by his cousin. And as
soon as his cousin smelled trouble, he
ran from Montana to Florida to Jordan,
disappeared in Jordan, and nobody's ever
seen him again.
Wow.
Elizabeth.
John, I was wondering why you think this
has happened now and why is it also that
the mainstream press has really kind of
ignored this story today? That it
doesn't seem to be really on the radar
of most people.
It's his own show.
Yeah.
Yeah, right.
Like my own show which totally ignored
this news today.
Um for a couple of reasons. Number one,
I think that Donald Trump really really
wants a scalp. I think Donald Trump
secretly wishes that he had been a
general or a war hero or something
special that he could pin medals on his
chest. He'll never have those medals on
his chest.
It doesn't matter what he does now. It
doesn't matter that he's become
president. But to be the guy that
finally convicts the mastermind of the
9/11 attacks after
what two previous presidents couldn't do
it?
Um that's that's quite a trophy. I think
he's doing it for for his own very
selfish purposes. But why is the
mainstream media um ignoring it? I think
for the same reason my own show ignored
it today. I think people generally don't
care anymore. You know, 18 years have
passed and uh there's a whole
generation, you know, just a couple of
months ago we lost a soldier in
Afghanistan. He was the first one that
we've ever lost who was born after the
9/11 attacks.
And I think that people just really
don't care anymore.
That is a really sad statement to, you
know, about our society after after
everything that 9/11 preceded. I think
that's extremely depressing outlook, but
seems to be accurate. I can't think of
another reason why this would get so
little press.
I I agree with you.
why this would petrol a war right now
and yet
nobody cares about convicting the
individuals who involved. Of course,
this should be in a civilian court. I I
attended and I reported for the Boston
Globe in 1999
trial in the Southern District of New
York,
United States versus Osama bin Laden. It
was about the African Embassy bombings.
It was in a civilian court. Mary Jo
White was there in the in the courtroom.
I saw her there. She was of course the
she prosecuted on there the US the
Southern District in New York.
And it was a civilian trial and I saw
her Al-Qaeda guys on the stand and there
was a jury of civilians there and they
convicted these guys. And I thought
that's the way it was going to go until
the Bush administration came along and
decided on this entire
black sites Guantanamo and military
courts. And the whole thing's been a
joke all along, hasn't it? All of these
They had various types of
proceedings over the years as well
already in Guantanamo, haven't they?
They tried to see whether people should
stay there or not.
In fact, they've already declassified
22,000 pages of documents from those
hearings. Those hearings have been
dragging on since
since what, 2003?
And and we're no closer to to justice
for anybody than we were in 2003. You
know, Joe, you go through some of these
22,000 pages of documents and all you
see is this nonsensical back and forth
and back and forth between the
prosecution and the defense where the
defense is winging it. And they're
winging it because they're not permitted
access to any of the statements that
their own clients have made.
It's all deemed to be classified and
even though they have security
clearances, those clearances aren't high
enough
Uh, allow them access to the information
that they need to defend their clients.
What could they possibly get in
discovery by October 1st, which is only
2 months from now? They're they're
supposed to
Yeah.
Uh, the the government's supposed to
turn over materials to the defense in
discovery. What can they possibly hope
to get?
Yeah. Uh, I saw that when the New York
Times uh, broke the story this
afternoon. Uh, my my guess is they can't
hope to get much of anything because
whatever it is that the prosecution
still has that they deem to be important
enough to use in a um, in a uh, trial
you know they're going to fight tooth
and nail to withhold from the defense.
My guess is
that this is going to get bogged down in
litigation
and that January 2021 date is just going
to be pushed farther and farther back.
And there'll be less and less interest
in the event that spawned mass
surveillance, illegal mass surveillance
wars on several and several countries
that continue to this moment.
Yes.
This is the genesis of it. If they if
they actually try these men in a fair
way, which we you established that most
likely will not be uh, that could put
some kind of a bow on this thing and
that's normally what we do in the
American system is to find someone who's
guilty and try them fairly and then
punish them. But instead we got wars and
surveillance and now nobody cares about
the damn trial.
Yeah, that's that's right. We we really
could achieve closure. We achieved
closure with Richard Reid, the shoe
bomber, with Omar Abdel-Rahman, the
blind sheikh. We've achieved closure
over and over and over. We've tried
terrorists in civilian courts over and
over and over again all across the
country, all through our history. So
what made these men so special, so
terrible, so bad, so dangerous that they
had to be kept in Cuba? Well, the only
thing that did was the was the arrogance
and the ego of Dick Cheney and the
weakness of leadership of George Tenet.
That's why we're still in this
predicament as far as I'm concerned.
Now, I'm going to let you go because you
have to get a plane, John, but uh, you
were saying before we came on the air
that Sheikh Khalid Mohammed, who is
named as one of the defendants in this
trial, was you believe the mastermind.
I do. I do believe he's the he was the
mastermind. We didn't know his name. We
didn't know that his name was Khalid
Sheikh Mohammed. We knew only that there
was a man known to his compatriots as
Mukhtar, m u k h t a r, who had been the
mastermind of the Bojinka operation,
which was a plan in 1996 to hijack
more than a dozen 747s from Manila and
then fly them into buildings along the
US West Coast. That That was foiled.
But we we knew that there was this bad
man out there. We didn't know his name.
Abu Zubaydah finally gave us his name.
Actually, let me clarify that. Abu
Zubaydah gave the name Khalid Sheikh
Mohammed to Ali Soufan over the course
of a of a conversation over tea and
dates,
not to Mitchell Jessen as a result of
the CIA's torture program.
That was the actionable intelligence
that Abu Zubaydah gave us and it did not
come from torture.
Which is valuable evidence, obviously.
Indeed.
So, John, Elizabeth, if you have a final
question, we'll let John go.
No, thank you, John, for joining us. I
don't want to hold you up from your
flight, but incredible insight. I'm glad
at least a couple of people are asking
questions about this and covering it
today.
to keep an eye on this story. That's for
damn sure. And thank you
that you have.
Okay. Thank you for joining us.
Thank you.